{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In 2017, this state’s town of Cleveland settled a 52-year-long court case about the segregation of its public schools. This state passed a law banning felons from college admission, then charged a black applicant with false voter registration and convicted him in absentia on the same day. Ultimately, Robert F. Kennedy ordered U.S. Marshals to desegregate this state’s flagship university on the request of Governor Ross Barnett, who refused to do it without being coerced. For ten points, name this US state where James Meredith attended college in Oxford.",
      "answer": "Mississippi"
    },
    {
      "question": "One side in this war benefited from trees planted as target markers years prior by a spy in the Ministry of Defense. The losing side in this war renewed its commitment to “no peace” and “no negotiation” in the Khartoum Resolution. This war began with Operation Focus, a surprise attack that crippled the losing side’s air force, contributing to that side’s loss of the Sinai Peninsula and the Golan Heights. For ten points, name this 1967 war, a quick victory for Israel over an Arab coalition.",
      "answer": "Six-Day War"
    },
    {
      "question": "Members of this group collaborated on an unfinished opera-ballet about the Polabian Slavs in the 10th century titled Mlada. An 1185 campaign against the Cumans and their Khans is the subject of an opera from this group that features the Polovtsian Dances; another work from this group is about the fall of the Rurikids. The composers of Prince Igor and Boris Godunov, Alexander Borodin and Modest Mussorgsky, were members of, for ten points, what nationalist movement in 19th century Russian music?",
      "answer": [
        "The Mighty Handful",
        "the Mighty Five",
        "Moguchaya kuchka"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man recognized the authority of Philip Augustus over Angevin lands in the Treaty of Le Goulet, but later tried to challenge those claims in the disastrous Battle of Bouvines [boo-veen]. This man was excommunicated by Innocent III after refusing to allow Stephen Langton be appointed Archbishop of Canterbury. This king was cornered at Runnymede by discontented barons, forcing this man to curb his own power to tax and promise trials by jury. For ten points, name this English king who signed the Magna Carta.",
      "answer": [
        "King John",
        "John I",
        "John Lackland"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This politician was accused of taking bribes from the Union Pacific Railroad in the Mulligan Letters. This politician was endorsed in a speech by Robert Ingersoll, leading to him being nicknamed the “Plumed Knight.” This politician lost the support of many Catholics when a pastor denounced Democrats as the party of “Rum, Romanism, and Rebellion”. For ten points, name this senator and so-called “Continental Liar” from Maine who was defeated by Grover Cleveland in the election of 1884.",
      "answer": "James G. Blaine"
    },
    {
      "question": "This author described his annoyance with police calling him “Joe” in his autobiographical memoir Joseph Anton, named for his pseudonym. A novel by this author depicts Muhammad’s early followers alongside stories about Jibreel Farishta and Saladin Chamcha. 2019’s Quichotte was written by, for ten points, what British-Indian novelist who became the subject of a fatwa from Ayatollah Khomeini for his novel The Satanic Verses?",
      "answer": "Salman Rushdie"
    },
    {
      "question": "Akingofthislocationwasbelievedtohaveinventedthechariottohidehisserpentinefeet.Ericthonius ruled this location, as did another serpent-legged king named Cecrops, who judged an olive tree to be better than a salt water spring. Another king of this city died when his son returned with black sails on his boat after slaying the Minotaur. The mythological figures Theseus and Aegeus ruled, for ten points, what ancient Greek city whose origin myth includes Poseidon losing a contest to be its namesake?",
      "answer": [
        "Athens",
        "Attica before “city” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Participants in this event were captured at Arthur Allen’s home, which became known as its leader’s “Castle.” This event was sparked by a Doeg raid on the farm of Thomas Matthews. The namesake of this event issued a Declaration of the People and massacred the Occoneechee people. John Ingram replaced the leader of this event after he died of dysentery. Governor William Berkley hung 23 men for participation in, for ten points, what 1676 rebellion that led to the burning of Jamestown?",
      "answer": "Bacon’s Rebellion"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s namesake stand was a cast iron base used to keep his subject still. This man, who depicted an elderly Andrew Jackson at his estate and created portraits of Edgar Allan Poe, used the albumen print technique after originally working with daguerreotypes. Ulysses S. Grant places his hand on a tree in a work by, for ten points, what artist whose exhibition The Dead of Antietam displayed the gruesome nature of the Civil War via photography?",
      "answer": "Mathew Brady"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man signaled his newfound status by changing his last name to include “Novyi.” Enemies of this man accused him of joining the Khlysty sect. This man was lured into the Moika Palace on the night of his downfall, and when he drank Felix Yusupov’s cyanide-laced wine without any effect, he was shot three times. This man had gained royal influence due to his apparent ability to stop the bleeding of Alexei, the hemophiliac heir of the tsar. For ten points, name this Russian mystic who advised Nicholas II.",
      "answer": "Grigori Rasputin"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these events probably killed Union soldier Boston Corbett, the man who shot John Wilkes Booth. Wisconsin’s Green Island Lighthouse had to be kept on during the day during one of these events that may have been caused by fragments of Comet Biela. Peshtigo was struck by one of these events on the same day that one began on DeKoven Street, possibly after a cow kicked over a lantern. For ten points, name this type of natural disaster that destroyed thousands of wooden houses in Chicago in 1871.",
        "answer": [
          "fires",
          "additional information, like the Great Peshtigo Fire",
          "Great Chicago Fire"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "According to an anti-Irish legend, the Great Chicago Fire began when this woman’s cow kicked over a lantern.",
        "answer": [
          "Catherine O’Leary",
          "Mrs. O’Leary"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire used the paiza seal to indicate officials authorized to use the stations of the Yam supply route. This empire conquered the Kingdom of Dali and installed a local governor known as a Tusi [tu-szu]. This empire was betrayed by its vassal, the Western Xia, and it finished one conquest at the Battle of Yamen on the Pearl River Delta. After crossing the Yangtze, this empire was able to defeat the Southern Song Dynasty. For ten points, name this empire that conquered China under the rule of Genghis and Kublai Khan.",
        "answer": "Mongol Empire"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In Russia, the Yam system survived the fall of this khanate, an offshoot of the Mongol Empire that was founded by Batu Khan in 1242.",
        "answer": [
          "Golden Horde",
          "Ulug Ulus",
          "Kipchak Khanate",
          "Ulus of Jochi"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man created the Bureau of Indian Affairs while serving as Secretary of War under James Monroe. This man, who became Secretary of State after the USS Princeton disaster, declared slavery to be a “positive good” in an 1837 Senate speech. The Tariff of Abominations was vehemently opposed by this author of the South Carolina Exposition and Protest. For ten points, name this member of the Great Triumvirate who often stood for states’ rights in the Senate.",
        "answer": "John C. Calhoun"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Tariff of Abominations produced this crisis, which centered on whether or not states could choose to ignore federal law.",
        "answer": "Nullification crisis"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Cecile Renault attempted to assassinate this man and smiled at her execution. This man’s downfall came after Joseph Fouch´e managed to rally support against the Law of 22 Prairial. This man, who attempted to create a Deist religion known as the Cult of the Supreme Being, was called the “incorruptible.” The Thermidorian Reaction against this man ended with his beheading. For ten points, name this leader of the Committee of Public Safety during the Reign of Terror in the French Revolution.",
        "answer": "Maximilien Robespierre"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Robespierre’s Cult of the Supreme Being was meant to replace an atheistic “Cult of” this enlightenment concept that was promoted by people like Jacques H´ebert.",
        "answer": "Cult of Reason"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Description acceptable. During this conflict, panic broke out after John Feeks was killed above a watching crowd. During this conflict, engineer Harold Brown campaigned against a “danger from sudden deaths” by killing dogs in public. Anachronistic claims place the death of Topsy the Elephant during this conflict, in which one side lobbied to have the other side carry out the first execution by electric chair. For ten points, name this late 19th century “war” over the marketplace for electric power that was “lost” by Thomas Edison’s DC technology.",
        "answer": [
          "War of the Currents",
          "Battle of the Currents",
          "descriptions of the competition between AC and DC power, alternating and direct current electricity, etc."
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the War of the Currents, Harold Brown challenged this advocate of AC power to a “duel” in which each would be shocked by increasing amounts of their preferred form of electricity; the first to quit would have lost, but this inventor of the air brake declined the duel.",
        "answer": "George Westinghouse"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city was founded after William Blaxton allowed settlers to encroach on his land for potable water. The nearby Beacon Hill led this city to be known as Trimountaine in its early days. This city was the site of the Antinomian heresy, which led to the banishment of Anne Hutchinson. Puritans aboard the Arbella founded this city shortly after signing the Cambridge Agreement. For ten points, name this preeminent city of colonial Massachusetts.",
        "answer": "Boston"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Puritan minister gave the “Model of Christian Charity” sermon on board the Arbella en route to the Massachusetts Bay Colony.",
        "answer": "John Winthrop"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Generals for this city included Sebastiano Venier and Agostino Barbargio, who both fought against the Ottomans in the Battle of Lepanto. The word “ghetto” originated from this city, which was attacked by Pope Julius II’s League of Cambrai. A ring was annually dropped into the water in this city’s Marriage of the Sea ceremony, which was overseen by its doge. For ten points, name this “Most Serene Republic,” an Italian city-state known for its many canals.",
        "answer": "Venice"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This blind doge led Venice from 1192 to 1205. His forces were excommunicated because they sacked Zara, even before they attacked Constantinople.",
        "answer": "Enrico Dandolo"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2004, Dorval Airport was renamed to honor this leader, whose government supported the construction of Mirabel Airport in the 1970s in the hopes of phasing out Dorval. This leader signed the Official Languages Act, which supported both English and French in federal government services; that act was signed a year after this man succeeded Lester Pearson. This man served as Prime Minister for over 15 years, the third longest tenure in Canadian history. For ten points, name this Canadian politician, the father of modern Prime Minister Justin.",
        "answer": "Pierre Trudeau"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mirabel International Airport served this major Canadian city for nearly 30 years before transitioning into a cargo-only airport in 2004. Mirabel was unpopular because it is a decidedly long drive away from the island in the Saint Lawrence River on which this city was built.",
        "answer": "Montreal"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "The Alamo",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Modern US state where the Battle of the Alamo took place.",
          "answer": "Texas"
        },
        {
          "question": "City in that state that includes the Alamo.",
          "answer": "San Antonio"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mexican general who led the attack on the Alamo.",
          "answer": [
            "Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna",
            "Antonio de Padua Maria Severino Lopez de Santa Anna y Perez de Lebron"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "“King of the Wild Frontier” and former Tennessee politician who died at the Alamo.",
          "answer": "Davy Crockett"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pioneer and knifeman who fought despite being bedridden at the Alamo.",
          "answer": "James Bowie"
        },
        {
          "question": "Author of the “Victory or Death” letter who died at the Alamo.",
          "answer": "William Travis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Woman who confirmed several legendary details about the Alamo after surviving with her daughter Angelina.",
          "answer": "Susanna Dickinson"
        },
        {
          "question": "So-called “coward of the Alamo,” supposedly the only man to choose to leave before fighting broke out.",
          "answer": "Louis “Moses” Rose"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Start of World War II",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Strategy of “lightning war” used by Nazi Germany in its opening invasions.",
          "answer": "blitzkrieg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that was invaded by the Nazis to start the war after the Gleiwitz incident.",
          "answer": "Poland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Date on which that invasion began.",
          "answer": "September 1, 1939"
        },
        {
          "question": "Neutrality pact between the Soviets and Nazis that was secretly signed a week before that invasion.",
          "answer": "Molotov-von Ribbentrop Pact"
        },
        {
          "question": "Defensive line built by the French in the 1930s to buy time for mobilization; it was weak along the Ardennes, which the Nazis exploited.",
          "answer": "Maginot Line"
        },
        {
          "question": "War between the Soviets and Finland in the opening months of World War II, followed by the Continuation War.",
          "answer": "Winter War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for the first eight months of the war which were, except for a brief French invasion into southwestern Germany, mostly quiet on the western front.",
          "answer": [
            "Phony War",
            "Sitzkrieg"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "That brief French offensive, which was aborted after the Nazis quickly closed the eastern front.",
          "answer": "Saar Offensive"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Philippines Independence",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "European country from which the Philippines declared its independence in 1898.",
          "answer": "Spain"
        },
        {
          "question": "Non-European country that gained the Philippines from that country and controlled it until 1946.",
          "answer": [
            "United States of America",
            "USA",
            "America"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1946 treaty, signed in the Philippine capital, granting independence.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Manila"
        },
        {
          "question": "First civilian governor of the Philippines, serving from 1901 to 1903; he later served as President.",
          "answer": "William Howard Taft"
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolutionary republic, named for a Philippine language, that fought for independence.",
          "answer": "Tagalog Republic"
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolutionary who served as first President of the Philippines.",
          "answer": "Emilio Aguinaldo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Muslim-majority ethnic group that fought a fourteen-year insurgency in the southern Philippines.",
          "answer": [
            "Moro people",
            "Moro Rebellion, Insurgency, etc."
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Secret independence movement that formed after Jos´e Rizal was exiled.",
          "answer": "Katipunan"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) According to legend, because a ruler of this empire asked for the head of the Maharaja of Zabag, the ruler’s head was instead taken by the Maharaja. Rajendra Chola helped this empire defeat the Tambralinga Kingdom and the Srivijayas in the (20 pts)",
        "11th century. The Baphuon temple and Baray water resevoirs were built by this empire. The diplomat Zhou Daguan was sent to this empire, traveling through (10 pts)",
        "Tonle Sap lake. Several kings named Jayavarman ruled, for ten points, what empire that built Angkor Wat in what is now Cambodia?"
      ],
      "answer": "Khmer Empire"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This group was criticized for employing the Gehlen Organization in launching Operation Bohemia, where a Czech detonator was successfully secured. This group’s leader, William Colby, helped compile a set of documents known as the “Family Jewels” that detailed their (20 pts)",
        "assassination efforts. Carlos Armas was supported by this group during Operation PBSUCCESS, in which the United Fruit Company convinced this group to (10 pts)",
        "launch a coup d’etat in Guatemala. Allen Dulles once led, for ten points, what American foreign intelligence service?"
      ],
      "answer": "Central Intelligence Agency or CIA"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Clement VII contradicted Catholic canon law by mourning the sack of Rome with one of these objects, creating a fashion that lasted for successive popes. Grace Bedell suggested the use of this object. Walter Hawkins published an 1845 paper about a (20 pts)",
        "tax on these objects, for which a token was given after the tax was paid. Flemish painter Anthony (10 pts)",
        "van Dyck popularized a style of this fashion, and Peter the Great passed a tax on boyars who chose to wear them. For ten points, name this fashion choice that Abraham Lincoln was inspired to adopt because “all the ladies like whiskers.”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "beards",
        "facial hair in general, but"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This philosopher, who described a compound of matter and form which he termed hylomorphism, divided tragic theater into elements such as opsis, mythos, and ethos in what is believed to be the first work of (20 pts)",
        "literary theory. This philosopher fled Athens in 323 BC after the death of his patron king. (10 pts)",
        "Poetics, Metaphysics, and the Nicomachean Ethics were written by, for ten points, what Greek philosopher, a student of Plato who tutored Alexander the Great?"
      ],
      "answer": "Aristotle"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A film produced during this war depicts a leader who is jailed by Marcas the blacksmith. The Hello Girls operated in this war, as did the farmerettes. During this war, a mysterious explosion that was suspected to be sabotage occurred at (20 pts)",
        "Black Tom Island. Charles Lathrop Pack ran a War Garden Commission in this war, for which “wheatless Wednesdays” and “meatless Tuesdays” were created. The (10 pts)",
        "Zimmerman Telegram helped push the U.S. to declare war in, for ten points, what war in which the lost propaganda film The Kaiser, the Beast of Berlin was produced?"
      ],
      "answer": "World War I"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader defeated the Helvetii at the Battle of Bibracte and the Nervii at the Battle of the Sabis. This man, who was rumored to have had an affair with King Nicomedes in his youth, was once captured by a group of (20 pts)",
        "pirates who he later had crucified. Vercingetorix was defeated at the siege of (10 pts)",
        "Alesia by this man, who legendarily declared “the die is cast” upon crossing the Rubicon to instigate a civil war. For ten points, name this Roman dictator who was assassinated by conspirators on the Ides of March."
      ],
      "answer": "Gaius Julius Caesar"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Controversies flared over the necessity of HOM, PP, and IT redactions in this document. After the release of this document, Jerry Nadler subpoenaed a former White House Counsel to testify before the House Judiciary Committee. (20 pts)",
        "Kellyanne Conway called for apologies in the wake of this document, whose redacted form was published by Attorney General William (10 pts)",
        "Barr. Rod Rosenstein commissioned this document after Jeff Sessions recused himself in 2017. For ten points, name this Special Council investigation report prepared by a former FBI director concerning Russian interference in the 2016 election."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Mueller Report",
        "Report on the Investigation into Russian Interference in the 2016 Presidential Election"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s relationship with Catalina Ju´arez infuriated her brother, Diego Vel´azquez de Cu´ellar, until he finally married her. This man assembled troops to fight against the expedition of Panfilo de (20 pts)",
        "Narvaez while a small detachment under Pedro Alvarado was left behind and massacred during La (10 pts)",
        "Noche Triste. This man benefited from an alliance with Tlaxcala [t’lahsh-ca-LA] and the work of the translator La Malinche [mah-leen-chay] in his campaign against Montezuma. For ten points, name this conquistador who defeated the Aztec Empire."
      ],
      "answer": "Hern´an Cort´es"
    }
  ]
}